Guide to the Barrell family papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Barrell Family Papers,
1751-1929
[Bulk Dates: 1791-1889].
Barrell Family.
1.25 linear ft. (3 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY.10027
MS#0082
4078972
The collection consists primarily of personal correspondence between members of the Barrell family in London, the United States, Barbados, and Demerara which was then a part of British Guiana. The collection also contains several family chronicles, a diary and cashbook belonging to Theodore Barrell, autograph albums belonging to Walter Newberry Barrell and Theodora Barrell, and photographs and silhouettes.
Historical Note
The Barrell Family were noted merchants and businessmen in London and in colonial Demerara, now part of Guyana.
Theodore Barrell, the son of Walter Newberry Barrell, a London-based businessman, was both in Boston in 1771. He spent most of his career working as a merchant in the Americas, including in Barbados where he met his wife Elizabeth Beckles Barrell (born November 18, 1783) and in Demerara.
Theodore Barrell died in Saugerties, New York in 1846.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of letters to Theodore Barrell from members of the Barrell family in London, the United States, Barbados. The collection also contains geneological chronicles, a diary and cashbook belonging to Theodore Barrell, autograph albums belonging to Walter Barrell and Theodora Barrell, an exercise book belonging to John Stayner Barrell, and silhouettes and photographs of the Barrell family and of their property.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1751-1853
Series II: Autograph Albums, Diaries, and Exercise Book, 1814-1874
Series III: Visual Materials, undated, 1864-1889
Series IV: Genealogical Material and Family Documents, 1804-1929
Series V: Books Owned by the Family
Subjects
Barrell, Walter.; Barrell, Theodore.; London (England)--Description and travel.; Barbados--Description and travel.; Guyana--Commerce.; Guyana--Description and travel.; Families--Barbados.; Families--Guyana.; Merchants.; Diaries.; Photoprints.; Autographs.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
M59 gift Walter E. Benjamin
Alternate Formats
Manuscripts and photographs are on microfilm.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1751-1853
  This series is composed of primarily letters from various members of the Barrell family to Theodore Barrell, There are also a few letters to other members of the Barrell family, however the bulk of the correspondence is addressed to Theodore. The largest single group comprises the letters of Walter Barrell in London to his son, Theodore who was then a merchant in Demarara. These letters mention such family affairs as births, deaths and marriages, business matters including payments received and payments due, and advice from father to son on interpersonal matters often including remarks on religion and faith. Some correspondence makes passing mention of the change of rule in Demarara from British to Dutch and then back to British rule again from 1802-1803 and the beginning of the Napoleonic Wars in Europe. The majority of the correspondence from other members of the family deals with major family events, health of family members and friends of the family and trade matters.
  - A-B, 1751-1841 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barrell, Abigail, 1794-1846 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barrell, Theodore, 1836-1845 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barrell, Walter to Theodore Barrell, 1781-1804 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barrell, William to Theodore Barrel, 1795-1803 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - C-Z, 1794-1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Massa, Theodora, 1837-1844 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Autograph Albums, Diaries, and Exercise Book, 1814-1881
  This series contains autograph books belonging to Theodore Barrell’s children, Walter Newberry Barrell and Theodora Barrell, a diary and cashbook belonging to Theodore Barrell from 1841 and an exercise book belonging to John Stayner Barrell dated 1814-1816.
  Theodore Barrell’s diary and cashbook of 1841 details his observations on subjects ranging from weather conditions to comparisions of different branches of the Christian faith. The diary and cashbook also lists cash receipts and expenditures and marks important historical dates and Barrell family events.
  John Stayner Barrell’s exercise book is mainly composed of his study of the French language including vocabulary, verb conjugations and extensive translations from English to French. The book also contains brief entries on such subjects as social customs in letter writing, shorthand notation, arithmetic and religion. The exercise book also contains lovingly illustrated family trees for the Barrell family and the Stayner family.
  This series also contains a diary compiled by Charles Barrell, Elizabeth Barrell, Elizabeth Massa, and Theodora Barrell including historical events as well as daily occurrences.
  - Barrell, Charles-- Diary, 1837-1881, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    (compiled with Elizabeth Barrell, Elizabeth Massa, and Theodora Barrell)
  - Barrell, John Stayner-- Exercise Book (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Barrell, Theodora-- Autograph and Commonplace Book, 1820-1826 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Barrell, Theodore-- Diary and Account Book, 1841 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Barrell, Walter Newberry-- Autograph and Commonplace Book, 1823-1827 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Visual Materials, Undated, 1864-1889
  This series contains a small number of photographs of members of the Barrell Family and property owned by the family. There are also two silhouettes.
  - Photographs, undated, 1864-1889 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Silhouettes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    (one is of Theodora Barrell)
- Series IV: Geanealogical Material and Family Documents
  This series is comprised of notes about the genealogy of the Barrell Family and family and legal documents such as land deeds and wills.
  - Notes on Barrell Family genealogy, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Barrell Family Chonology, 1579-1849 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Barrell Family Chronology, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    (compiled by Charles Barrell and enclosed in a letter to his cousin)
  - Conveyance of Property by Theodore Barrell to Ferdinand Massa, 1831 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notice of Lottery or Sale of Theodore Barrell's Property in Demerara, 1804 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    (printed broadside)
  - History of the Gall Estate (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gall, Elizabeth
    - Last Will and Testament, 1813 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Copy of a Paper Handed to Miss Gall, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Barrell, Theodore-- Sketches of the Demerary Incidents 2nd September 1791 to 29th March 1800 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Mscellaneous Items (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series V: Books Owned by the Barrell Family
  - The Bouquet: A Selection of Poems owned by Elizabeth Barrell (Box 3)
  - De L'education des Enfans owned by Theodore Barrell (Box 3)